Guide to the Middletown Scientific Association Records, 1871 - 1976
Middletown Scientific Association Records, 1871 - 1976
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Middletown Scientific Association (Conn.)
1000-160
2
4
The Middletown Scientific Association was founded on March 17, 1871 by Wesleyan University faculty and residents of Middletown, Connecticut. Its purpose was to encourage scientific investigation and curiosity among members and to receive papers from members and other scientists regarding popular topics in all fields of science, history of science, and education of science.
The Middletown Scientific Association Records include minutes, reports, a scrapbook, administrative records, and other historical materials which document the organization's operations from 1871 until it disbanded in 1968.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Provenance unknown.
Historical Note
The Middletown Scientific Association was founded on March 17, 1871 by Wesleyan University faculty and residents of Middletown, Connecticut. Its purpose was to encourage scientific investigation and curiosity among members and to receive papers from members and other scientists regarding popular topics in all fields of science, history of science, and education of science. The association was one of the very first town and gown organizations at Wesleyan University. Founding members included John Johnston, E. P. Barrows, Frederic Gardiner, R. G. Pike, H. D. A. Ward, J. M. Van Vleck, J. C. Van Benschoten, W. N. Rice, C. T. Winchester, G. Browne Good, Noah Cressy, E. B. Nye, G. W. Burke, W. W. Coe, H. E. Sawyer, J. H. Emerson, F. D. Edgerton, J. P. Taylor, S. W. Noyes, F. H. Newhall, C. S. Harrington, Joseph Cummings, A. M. Shew, and A. W. Hazen. Members of the association, in addition to Wesleyan faculty, included physicians, ministers, and teachers. Women were admitted into membership beginning in 1880.
Regular meetings were often held in the Hall Laboratory of Chemistry, Scott Laboratory of Physics, and Shanklin Laboratory of Biology at Wesleyan University. Occasional field meetings were held, during which members would learn first-hand about botany, geology, and other topics of natural history. Early in the association's history, papers were given at regular meetings on a variety of scientific topics in all fields, usually by members of the association, and occasionally by outside scientific experts. As membership grew, lecturers were more frequently invited from abroad to speak to the association.
The Middletown Scientific Association disbanded in 1968, after attendance at regular meetings was limited to those members who had been invited to dinner to meet with the lecturer. Though membership numbers and satisfaction with the organization remained high, there appeared to be a consensus among members that individuals were too busy to attend. The final meeting was held on April 8, 1968.
Collection Overview
Collection contains the records of the Middletown Scientific Association, spanning the years 1871 to 1976. These records document the proceedings of meetings from the association's founding in 1871 until its cessation in 1968, the administration of the association, and its association with the town of Middletown and Wesleyan University. Included are minutes, meeting announcements, treasury and presidents' reports, clippings, a scrapbook, and other historical materials. Of note are the announcements and clippings regarding talks given to the association by prominent scientists such as Italian physicist and Nobel Prize winner Enrico Fermi in 1940, and the association's resolutions on matters effecting the scientific community at large.
Collection Arrangement
Materials are organized into three series: Meeting Records, Administrative Materials, and Historical Materials.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Faculty.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History.; Middletown Scientific Association (Conn.); Middletown (Conn.)--History.; Science --Philosophy --History.; Science --United States --Societies, etc.; Education--Science--United States.; Scrapbooks.; Science--United States--History.; Scientists --Social aspects --United States.; Science --Social aspects --United States.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Meeting Records, 1871-1968
  This series contains meeting records of the Middletown Scientific Association, spanning the years 1871 to 1968. It is primarily comprised of minutes and meeting announcements. Minute books also typically contain the association's constitution and bylaws, and one book of the secretary's records contains additional materials such as obituaries of prominent members and treasury reports.
  This series is organized into two subseries: Minutes and Meeting Announcements. Each subseries is arranged roughly in chronological order.
  - Minutes
    - Minute book and constitution, 1871-1876 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Minute book and constitution, 1877-1885 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Annual address of the president, 1881 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Minute book and annual report, 1885-1896, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Secretary's records, 1896-1926 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Contains minutes, resolutions, annual reports, treasury reports, meeting notices, obituaries of prominent members, membership application cards, constitution, and list of members.
    - Minutes, 1940 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Minutes, 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Meeting Announcements
    - Scrapbook, 1882-1937 (Box 2)
      Contains annual reports, clippings, list of members, obituaries of prominent members, and meeting announcements.
    - Meeting announcements, 1897-1968 (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
- Administrative Materials, 1901-1971
  Contains correspondence and financial records, documenting the administration of the association from 1905 to 1971.
  - Correspondence, 1905, 1963-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Membership cards, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Cash book and ledger, 1940-1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Check stubs, 1954-1961 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Other financial records, 1963-1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Historical Materials, 1871-1976
  Contains clippings, historical notes about the association, papers presented to the association, and other material pertaining to the history of the Middletown Scientific Association.
  - Clippings and printed material, 1871-1963 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Rice, W. N. "Middletown Scientific Association,", 1937 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Burford, M. G. Brief history of Middletown Scientific Association, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Seeger, Raymond J. "On Galileo's Philosophy of Science - In Retrospect,", 1964 September 16 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Sikorsky, Igor I. "VS-300 Helicopter,", 1941 December 9 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - WCNX Radio vignettes schedule, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)